I'm filming this video on the hip thrust
to urge you to use common sense when you
stumble across information online
pertaining to the hip thrust exercise. I
can tell you some some of my personal
experiences. I've been lifting weights
for 25 years, personal training for 20
years, and for the past 10 years, I've
been performing and prescribing the hip
thrust. First of all, when I started
prescribing the hip thrust, my ability
to help my clients develop their glutes
increased dramatically, but also back
pain went down. I've personally hip
thrusted 800 lb for one rep, uh 585 for
10 reps, 495 for 15 reps, and 405 for 20
reps. And my back health has never been
better, and my glutes have never been
bigger and stronger. So, uh, lately I've
been reading some some things online by
various people who are admonishing the
hip thrust, and this is to be expected.
The same thing happened to the bench
press, the squat, the deadlift. When
these exercises became popular, people
scoffed at them. First of all, people
don't like changed, and then a lot of
people are just jealous of the hip
thrust popularity. Some of them probably
really do think it's dangerous. But just
as legendary strength coach Dan John
said, "The squat is not dangerous, but
what you're what you're doing is
dangerous. How you're squatting is
dangerous." The same thing applies to
every exercise. If you squat with good
form, chances are you're going to be
okay. Same with deadlifts. Same with hip
thrust. But if you hip thrust with poor
form, then you're upping the risk a
little bit. So, in this video, I'm going
to show you how to perform the hip
thrust to dramatically reduce the risk
of ever developing any issues in your
back. So, the following tip I credit to
Ben Bruno. Ben and I were speaking on
the phone and he said, "You know, Brett,
one of the cues I give to my clients is
I have them look where the wall meets
the ceiling and it tends to fix
everything." And at that same time, I
was noticing whenever I'd have a client
doing the hip thrust that I put on
Instagram for the thumbnail, I'd see
that they were tucking their chin. And I
have this aha moment. So now IQ people
to just look forward. If there's a
mirror, look at yourself in the mirror.
And this fixes everything. And let me
tell you why. Over the years, I've had
plenty of clients look up when they're
at the top. They go like
this. And most of them are fine. The
vast majority never develop any back
pain when doing it that way. But every
once in a while, maybe like one in five
clients will start to develop issues
when they do that. The reason why I'll
explain with skelly in a minute. If you
look straight forward in the mirror like
this and then keep your gaze there the
whole time. Here's what happens. You
come up and then right here your chin
starts to tuck but it keeps your ribs
down. Your chest doesn't pop up. So your
ribs stay down. You come up and then
right here it's glutes pushing the hips
straight up. So you have this nice flat
torso and the hips they don't go into
anterior pelvic tilt. They might
slightly posterior pelvic tilt but it
keeps everything good. Here's what it
looks like when you use weight. So I'm
going
to roll the bar into
position. Get my legs
up. Take a deep breath.
[Applause]
And notice that my gaze stays forward
the entire time. When you do it this
way, you can do any rep range. You can
do the heaviest weight you can do for
one rep with that form and you'll be
fine. You can do three reps, you can do
five reps, you can do 10 reps, you can
do 20 reps, you can do sets of 50 if you
want, as long as you keep that form. But
if you go so heavy that you end up not
being able to do this and you end up
looking up, watch what
happens. Chest pops up. Now I'm in
spinal hyperextension. Now I can create
some issues. And on the same lines, if
you're repping out and you get, you
know, to a rep that's really hard and
then you squeeze out a couple more, but
you go like
this again, chest up. So, you need to
have a diligence to stop the set before
that happens. And it's the same thing
for the squat and the deadlift. You
know, if you're deadlifting and you
start to round, the set ends. You don't
just keep squeezing reps out while
letting your back position do whatever
it feels like. You have to develop the
grit and the knowledge and the
consistency and the, you know, the the
discipline to keep your form in check.
So, here's Skellyy who's going to help
out here. If you look up, you will, and
this isn't very flexible, but you can
see that everything's going to come up.
the ribs flare, the chest comes up, and
the spine hyperextends. And when the
spine and also the pelvis will anterly
rotate. So, it's like you're cranking on
these to reach greater heights. When
that happens, there's these bones in the
back of the vertebrae that can jam
together. You can start to to develop
issues like spondylloyis,
spondyolythesis,
um facet joint injuries, and things like
that. And that's probably what's going
on with a lot of people when they
develop back pain with the hip thrust.
And again, it only happens with maybe
like one in five people. And obviously
load and effort and volume and frequency
matter. How you design your program
matters. Some people get away with it,
some people don't. Obviously your
anatomy that plays a role in deter
determining whether you get back pain or
not. And there's also pain in and of
itself is complicated because pain
science there's a lot more than just
biomechanics and structure and posture
to pain. Nevertheless, when you do the
hip thrust, if you look forward and the
hips just pop up, you don't go into
hyperextension. The pelvis does not
anterly rotate. It's pushes straight up.
The glutes push the hips straight up.
And this doesn't hyper extend. The ribs
stay down. So the things you want are
forward eye gaze at the top. You want
chin tuck. You want flat torso, ribs
down. And you want the glutes pushing
the hips straight up, staying in neutral
or slightly posterior pelvic tilt. So,
if you do the hip thrust the way I just
showed you how to do, I'm almost
positive you'll be fine. Yes, there's
the occasional lifter that can't hip
thrust. There's also the occasional
lifter who can't squat or who can't
deadlift, but the vast majority of
people can. Every single client I've
ever trained for the last 10 years has
done hip thrust. Hundreds if not
thousands. I also have thousands of
people who have done my program strong
curves. Uh I have thousands of people
who have done my programs get glutes and
strong by breath. And I'm not
exaggerating. Over the last 10 years I
have probably received again I'm not
exaggerating probably a thousand emails
from people saying when I started doing
the hip thrust my back pain went away.
My you know and it could be for
different reasons. Maybe it has to do
with glute strength or confidence or
something, but I can tell you for
certain that the the hip thrust is good
for the body. It's good for the back.
It's good for the glutes. It's good for
the for everything. As long as you do it
right. So, do it that way. You should be
fine and you won't develop any back
issues. As long as your volume and
frequency is is is sound and reasonable.
It's just very important to kind of try
to see people's motives when you read
stuff online. I don't want to tell you
don't listen to people because it's
important to have an open mind and
listen to different people. But you got
to go with the experts. Speaking of
myself, I have my PhD in biomechanics.
I've done my doctoral thesis on hip
thrust versus squats. I've trained
hundreds and hundreds of clients over
the past decade in the hip thrust. I've
figured out exactly how to make it safe
and how to program it effectively and
I've done it myself. So if someone
doesn't have that kind of experience,
you know, you go to their social media
and you don't see anyone doing the hip.
You can go to my Instagram and my
YouTube channel and see people doing it
seven years ago and all along the way.
So this is evidence that I know what I'm
talking about. These other people that
write these articles and say these
things, they don't have those kind of
evidence that they understand the hip
thrust. And they're just like the people
who, you know, back in the day when
squats became popular said squats are
bad for your knees. They probably saw a
video of me doing it with heavy weight,
not knowing that I started off 10 years
ago using 185 pounds. My first workout
with a hip thrust was with 185. It took
me 3 years to use 4 405 lbs. It took me
5 years to use 495 and so on. And so
I've gradually progressed along the way.
So they might see a guy like me and go,
"Oh, I I can hip thrust what he can."
And they might jump right into 500 lb
and try it. and then they hurt
themselves or they don't feel it in the
right places is because they're, you
know, using too much weight to to
maintain proper form, the perform that I
showed you. You guys, I've had power
lifters who had to start off with body
weight hip thrust because it's just a
new movement. It's it strengthens and
range hip extension. They were lacking
that. They might have had really good
flex range hip extension strength, but
it's it's highly variable. I've also had
powerlifters start off with 500 lb. It's
very unique to the individual. And some
of these people probably, you know, jump
the gun and use heavy heavy load when
they should have started off really
light. They would have loved it. And so
rather than take the time and
investigate what they're doing wrong,
they just write an article or something
saying, "Oh my god, it's bad for you and
it's dangerous." And these same people
will say like, "It's more dangerous than
the squat or the deadlift." And I'm
like, "What? I do squats. I do
deadlifts. I do hip thrust. And when I'm
squatting the heaviest weight possible,
I'm scared. When I go for a new deadlift
PR, I've deadlfted 615 lbs and I've done
585 for two reps. I'm scared. You know,
some bad stuff can happen if you don't
have the discipline to keep your form in
check. Whereas with the hip thrust,
let's say I load the bar up with 850 lbs
and I try a one. Here's what happens. I
go
and I get it to here and I can't lock it
out. Maybe I go like this and go and
arch a little bit, but that usually
doesn't cause an injury. It's not very
common that you have an acute injury
with the hip thrust. They're usually
chronic. You arch too much, you
hyperextend for long periods of time,
for months on end, and you start
developing back pain. Whereas with the
squat or the deadlift, especially the
deadlift, if you round too much, you can
have an acute injury where you herniate
a disc or something like that. These do
not uh incriminate the exercise itself.
It incriminates the person for not
learning and understanding proper form.
Once again, the hip thrust is very safe.
Very safe. I've had zero injuries in 10
years of prescribing the hip thrust, and
I've only had one or two clients over
the last decade who even started
complaining of some discomfort. I can
always help fix people's form to where
they feel it in the glutes and they feel
it in the right areas. Now, if you are a
bodybuilder, if you're a physique
competitor, if you're just training to
improve your physique, you don't have to
do a one rep max hip thrust. You can do
most of your sets between 8 and 15 reps,
that will yield very good results. But
if you like variety, if you like going
heavy, if you're a powerlifter and you
think that heavy hip thrusts will
transfer better to your maximum deadlift
or squat strength, it's okay to do one
rep, it's okay to do three reps. You
just have to have the discipline to keep
your form in check. So, just remember,
I'm going to say this one last time. At
the top of a hip thrust, you want eye
gaze forward, chin tucked, ribs down,
torso flat, glutes pushing the hips all
the way up. If you do that everything
will be fine.